<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter, discovering the cause of Gods continuing wrath against the nation, notwithstanding the present endeavors of reformation: directing to the meanes of appeasing that wrath; and encouraging to constancy in those endeavours: / written with much judgement and pious affection, by Mr Nathaniel Rogers, a godly and learned Divine now in New-England, to a worthy member of the Honourable House of Commons, bearing date, Decemb. 17, 1643. Imprimatur Edmund Calamy.</title>
            <author>Rogers, Nathaniel, 1598-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1821</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E53_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23205</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871933</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871933</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155227</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155227)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 9:E53[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter, discovering the cause of Gods continuing wrath against the nation, notwithstanding the present endeavors of reformation: directing to the meanes of appeasing that wrath; and encouraging to constancy in those endeavours: / written with much judgement and pious affection, by Mr Nathaniel Rogers, a godly and learned Divine now in New-England, to a worthy member of the Honourable House of Commons, bearing date, Decemb. 17, 1643. Imprimatur Edmund Calamy.</title>
                  <author>Rogers, Nathaniel, 1598-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M. for Christopher Meredith at the Crane in Pauls Church-yard,,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLIV. [1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Puritan ideals of holiness.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 5th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Puritans --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Puritan Revolution, 1642-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155227:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER, DISCOVERING The Cauſe of GODS continuing wrath againſt the Nation, notwithſtanding the preſent endeavours of Reformation: <hi>DIRECTING</hi> To the Meanes of appeaſing that wrath; And <hi>Encouraging</hi> to Conſtancy in thoſe Endeavours: Written with much Judgement and Pious affection,</p>
            <p>By M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Nathaniel Rogers,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A godly and Learned Divine now in <hi>New-England,</hi> To a worthy Member of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, bearing Date, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 17, 1643.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Imprimatur</hi> EDMUND CALAMY.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> at the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, M.DC.XLIV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:155227:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155227:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H that I had, or could ſanctifie the Lord according to his manifold, and great adminiſtrations of late dayes in <hi>England</hi> our deare mother. It's not long ſince we were as men that dreamed dreames when we here at once heard of that which might have been the work of many yeares, ſuch a Parliament once more choſen and aſſembled: ſuch liberties granted unto it, ſuch acts done by it, for <hi>Scotland</hi> (whoſe peace and liberty procured by your counſels, and <hi>Englands</hi> willing charges, I hope ſhall not be wiped off from your account in the behalfe of the Land) againſt enemies of God, Religion, Church, State, ſuch tall cedars felled, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But how ſuddenly did the Lord bring a black cloud over the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a new preſentment of it had we, as lying in blood, rent with diviſion (even ſuch as ſcarce any cauſe but the Goſpell uſeth to make) filled with alarmes, the mart of all rich commodities, made the ſhop of artillery; the garden of pleaſure, the ſtage of warre in one part of the Countrey and another: ſome Worthies already fallen, beſides divers (no queſtion) though of leſſe name on earth, yet of precious account in Heaven: ſome pined in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, others ſpoiled of their eſtates, (not to mention miſerable <hi>Ireland</hi> made a very ſlaughterhouſe, whiles your home-affaires fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling your heads and hands, and emptying your purſes, give advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to thoſe blood-thirſty ſons of that ſcarlet-whore to execute that cruell rage, that cries to Heaven) In the midſt of all theſe ſad calamities, your ſelves, whom God hath honoured to ſerve him at ſuch a time, in that high Court, as Pilots and Marriners toyling night and day in a ſtorme (longer then that <hi>Paul</hi> was in) to ſave that precious Barke from ſhipwrack and utter ſubmerſion, with all that rich treaſure that God hath ſtored it with, eſpecially of precious Saints, more precious then the fine gold, though accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as earthen pitchers: It hath been matter of admiration unto
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155227:3"/>me often, to ſee how the Lord upholds that Houſe it ſelfe from diſſolution in many reſpects, that you know better, but that its He that hangs the earth upon nothing (<hi>Iob</hi> 26.7.) and thoſe whoſe hearts are faithfull, and cloſe to the worke, how their heads have held, and their ſpirits not been exhauſt, and hearts with wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe failed, and given over, who have ſo many various, weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, unuſuall caſes to attend: who were ſufficient for theſe things without divine aſſiſtance? But not to ſeeme to forget what I write by troubling you with long writing, be pleaſed to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand hereby our due reſpect to and remembrance daily, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt continually of the great and high worke that you have in hand: and our labours and travailing thoughts and deſires (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our condition and meaſure) to promote that Cauſe, which you have the heavieſt end of at preſent lying upon your hands: and we ſay and deſire the Lord daily to ſpeake to your hearts, what he oft did to his Worthies in their great employment: Feare not, but be cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>agious; you ſerve a great Lord, that is higher then the Kings of the earth, and ſhall reigne in <hi>Sion:</hi> in a victorious cauſe, however oft oppreſſed; and for a people that are deare unto God, his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which he will deliver, his Saints that ſhall reigne with Chriſt Jeſus. But why then are all theſe things befallen us, and where are all his miracles? &amp;c. [<hi>Iudg.</hi> 6.13.] I confeſſe its a caſe worthy enquiry, and the Lord give an anſwer of peace unto his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. It's true, that Antichriſt will not downe with caſe: not the woman bring forth the man-child, that ſhould rule all nations with a rod of iron, a ſon of the Church to reigne, without the painefull throwes, and bloody ſufferings of many Martyrs: <hi>Pharaoh</hi> would not eaſily let the people goe: We our ſelves inherited the Goſpell with a mercifull Reformation, not without the aſhes of many faithfull witneſſes in thoſe <hi>Marian</hi> dayes: yea how long was the Church in her painefull breeding, and bringing forth the Truth in the yeares and from under the tyranny of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of iniquity in the bitter perſecutions, and innumerable ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> and others of the ſame Religion, though of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall names: The two witneſſes were ſlaine after their ſad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſyings in ſackcloth, before they are taken up to Heaven: yet we muſt ſeeke a blameable reaſon from ſinfull ſons of men, as of the taking away the Truth, ſo of the withholding it from them: And
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155227:3"/>it's no uncharitable gueſſe to ſay, that the hearts of the people of <hi>England</hi> are not prepared for the receiving Chriſt Jeſus in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. This is obvious: yet the caſe ſticks, for the neereneſſe of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to this mercy, and the ſuddaine withdrawing of it againe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth the darkneſſe of it: Doth the Lord uſe to refuſe zealous Reformation eſpecially in the hands of men of authority, that hath made ſuch promiſes, if there were but one ſuch, &amp;c. <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.1. Yes! it's not without preſident. <hi>Iſrael</hi> would correct <hi>Benjamins</hi> unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall wickedneſſe defended with diabolicall pride and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, yet they looſe 40000. before they all can puniſh one ſuch Tribe, as vengeance it ſelfe would not ſuffer to live. <hi>Ioſiah</hi> is zealous in purging and reſtoring Gods worſhip, his heart of a moſt choice temper, his actions almoſt all non-paraile, matchleſſe and ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, yet it ſtands not: there were ſins before which God would not pardon, [2 <hi>King.</hi> 24.4.] no not to the acceſſaries, though they were to the principall, <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> I mean, but it was that thoſe repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not, but their hearts hung idolward. What remedy then? Truly you are the Body repreſentative, and there are many of the body perſonally, yea ſome of all rankes, whoſe ſincerity of Repentance, I am perſwaded the Lord would not refuſe. And I know your Faſts are many, and your care great that all the people of the Land ſhould obſerve them: Bleſſed be God! Only be pleaſed to give me leave to ſuggeſt one queſtion, which, it may be you can readily aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoyle, though my diſtance keeps me ignorant: Hath that Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe, which hath begun to caſt out, the perſons, and things that have ſo much offended God, and good men; hath it confeſſed the guilt of neglecting ſuch Reformation in former Parliaments, yea the rejecting of motions preſented that way: and juſtifying the then preſent ſtate of the Church, as being pure, &amp;c? Hath there beene any publike teſtimony of acknowledgement of the great ſinne of the Land in worſhiping Chriſt after the manner of Antichriſt, and ſhutting out the Ordinances of Chriſt, and polluting Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice with mens ſuperſtitions? <hi>Ezra</hi> began that zealous divorcement of ſtrange wives, which <hi>Shecaniah</hi> adviſed him to attempt, with his deepe abaſement for that great treſpaſſe, which in a moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and affectionate confeſſion he acknowledged they had been in ſo long unto the juſt bringing and continuing all thoſe evils that lay upon them. That amendment that is without confeſſion and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155227:4"/>conviction hath not depth and bottome enough for the Lord to ſay much upon. If they be aſhamed of their wayes then ſhew them the wayes of my houſe, <hi>Ezek</hi> 43.11. God knowes not what to doe with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> unleſſe by ſtripping themſelves of their ornaments they ſhew they were aſhamed of what they had done, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. God leaves <hi>Ephraim</hi> to his troubles, till he ſhould become guilty, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15. Is that Reformation pleaſing to God that is not of evill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by God? if ſo: the guilt ſhould firſt be yeelded, before the practiſe removed: It's the deceit of many a ſoule in his perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall eſtate, to be zealous in caſting off ſuch corrupt cuſtomes, as his ſoule never abhorred it ſelfe for former defilements thereby: and the truth is, the deceit lies in imperfection of conviction, humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, yea of mortification: and that evill which a man leaves without acknowledgement and ſenſe of his former offenſiveneſſe in ſuch way, doth but reſerve to himſelfe a liberty in caſe of more eaſie taking up, that which he laid downe. Were that Truth duly ſtated, by which Epiſcopacy, Ceremonies, &amp;c. are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, then ſhould God be duly juſtified, the ſinfulneſſe of former aberrations perceived, yeelded, cenſured and condemned, and a ſure ſtandard, and inflexible rule be laid for a perfect repairing and regulating future worke. It was alledged by a learned man in the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> when they were diſallowing ſome things (as I remember) that there is nothing falſe but becauſe it erres from ſomewhat that is true. If it were no offence to God to worſhip him, and diſpenſe the things of his houſe as they were: and yet it is good to remove them, and have them otherwiſe: then the government of his Church, and the manner of his worſhip is a matter indifferent, and indeterminate: and then Chriſt hath gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nothing: but the royall prerogative of his Kingdome is as much abaſed as it was before: and then he will ſay, <hi>Obedience is better then ſacrifice.</hi> But perhaps, what I write is needleſſe: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, my boldneſſe comming from ſincere deſire of your beſt ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and honour, and ſpeciall confidence of your pious candor, will be pardoned. My deſire and prayer is, that the Lord will rebuke Satan, and take away any defiled garments from <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> and <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubbabel,</hi> that ſhould hinder acceptance or ſucceſſe: yea ſo I write as one that acknowledge my ſelfe to have had a ſhare in thoſe provocations and pollutions, and want yet an heart to be meetly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155227:4"/>ſenſible of the wrong done to the Lord Jeſus therein, though the Scripture ſheweth example, and argument plentifull in that kind. Wherefore, <hi>Honoured Sir,</hi> if all be not right therein, improve I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, that zeale which God hath enkindled in your breaſt, and that intereſt that ſo long experience of your fidelity to the Cauſe of God hath bred you in the hearts of thoſe Noble ſpirits, whom I hope God hath raiſed up to be the repairers of breaches, the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of pathes to dwell in, to draw as many as you may unto ſuch a due humiliation before the Lord, not for other abominations, and crying wickedneſſes of the Land alone, but this which was the cauſe of the reſt, and of higher nature then the reſt, that the Lord Jeſus hath not been ſet up in his throne, but iniquity eſtabliſhed therein by a Law: and that ſo as ſcarce any reformed Church hath done beſides, and contrary to the teſtimony of many moſt able, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Confeſſors, <hi>Cartwrights, Brightmans,</hi> &amp;c. by their pens and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings: prevailing againſt that precious blood of holy <hi>Bates</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in priſons, the impoveriſhing families, and obſcuring of men of choice abilities, in learning, preaching, writing, caſt aſide for rotten traſh, the ſtarving of many Congregations, robbed of their profitable and painefull paſtors, and infinite wrong to ſoules, bodies, eſtates of Saints, and diſhonour to Chriſt, and that though by <hi>Bb.</hi> yet through either power conferred, or not taken away by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: the very Religion of the greateſt part of <hi>England</hi> being but formality and blind devotion ſtanding with groſſe profaneneſſe: the beſt Congregations forced to proſtrate themſelves to the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of men over their conſciences, and the moſt ſacred parts of his worſhip corrupted with ſuperſtitious mixtures: Oh what Repentance, and what publike teſtimonies of ſelf-condemning Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance doth the holy God expect, when as <hi>England</hi> hath beene a ſcandall to other Churches for theſe things: which being meetly performed, I hope the Lord would not be long abſent from coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and endeavours for his own honour. <hi>David</hi> himſelfe that was fetching up the Arke with ſo much zeale, met with a terrible check: and though he was diſpleaſed at the breach, yet he was faine to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the ſinne of not ſeeking God after the right manner before he could proſper in his moſt pious attempt. How many of the <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhemittes</hi> fell, that yet went to bid the Arke welcome among them: Well perhaps this <hi>Perizuzza,</hi> and this ſlaughter of the <hi>Bethſhemites</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:155227:5"/>was to prepare <hi>David</hi> and the people to ſanctifie the Lord in their hearts, and ſay, who is able to ſtand before this holy Lord God?</p>
            <p>Truly Sir, our eyes are looking up, waiting and hoping, that the Lord is doing ſome great work by you in theſe dayes: It's no ſmall joy to think how many now look upon that truth with patience &amp; inquiſition, that thought it a note of pride or hypocriſie to be med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling withall: and that now pens and tongues doe juſtifie that, which erewhile it was ſcarce tolerable to be practiſed here: you know what great things are expected of a long time from the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and I hope ſome of them are at the doore: But then what manner of perſons ought we to be, not only that ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but ſhall bring forth ſuch things unto the world: Truly, God is to be feared for his mercies, and if fearfull in praiſes, when Chriſt came to redeeme as a Son of Righteouſneſſe, yet who might abide the day of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming? When the Lord appeared to <hi>Moſes</hi> in a viſion, portending deliverance, and preparing him to be the deliverer of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage, he bad <hi>Moſes</hi> put off his ſhooes, for the place where he ſtood was holy ground, <hi>Exod,</hi> 3. When <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> ſaw a man with his ſword drawne, and underſtood, that he was the Angell of the Lords hoſt, for them, not againſt them, he fell on his face and worſhipped: and was told that ground was holy, and bidden to put off his ſhooe. Now the Lord, that hath choſen <hi>England</hi> to ſave it, help his <hi>Moſeſes,</hi> and his <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> to ſuch a peculiar holineſſe that he requires of thoſe whom he will delight to worke by: It's not by might, nor wit, but my Spirit: the barley cake tumbles down <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> tents, that is, <hi>Gideon</hi> humbled with ſuch a deſcription made of him in that divine dreame. Now the time is for ſuch as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was, to repaire <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> walls, men of faith, that will not be daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, men of innocency and goodneſſe, that cannot be blemiſhed, men of zeale that can neither endure Gods honour to be prophaned, nor peoples poverty to be oppreſſed by the greateſt whatſoever. And who but <hi>Nehemiah's</hi> could doe your work, and act your part at this day? who could have endured ſuch labours and diſcouragements? His enemies ſcoffe: at length they conſpire to be upon him from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very part: his own people complaine of the difficulty of the work, their weary ſhoulders with carrying burdens, the aboundance of rubbiſh ſtill remaining, never like to be overcome, <hi>Neh,</hi> 4, 3, 8, 10. yet he encourageth the people, puts himſelfe and his upon the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155227:5"/>taskes, puts not off his cloathes, watcheth, worketh, prayeth, and is at great charges inſtead of taking the wonted allowance of men in his place. Truly, when God hath ſuch work to doe, he raiſeth men of ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ſpirits: Bleſſed be our God, that hath raiſed up ſuch, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held their hearts in that Honourable Houſe of invincible courage, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and labours, whatever is become of others, whom the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligts not in, to honour them with ſuch choice work, as his Temple-work is. Be you aſſured that the hearts of the faithfull in <hi>Iſrael</hi> are towards the governours of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that offered themſelves willingly among the people, bleſſe ye the Lord, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 6. The poore deſpiſed of Chriſts flock here doe pray, whiles you watch and work, and in the ſenſe of the weight of your charge would gladly be putting ſtones under your armes, whiles with <hi>Moſes</hi> you are ſtretching out the rod of your authority and deliverance, and others are fighting againſt <hi>Amalck.</hi> And the good Lord ſtirre up the hearts of the people of the Land to cleave unto you, that as God hath made you as the two hundred heads of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> men that had underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the times, and what <hi>Iſrael</hi> ought to doe, and their brethren were at their commandment, 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 12.32. ſo you may be able to ſay as the Governours of <hi>Iudah,</hi> The inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> are our ſtrength in the Lord of hoſts their God, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.5. And certainly the true inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> they are a great ſtrengthening (though very few) not in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves indeed, but in their God who is the Lord of hoſts: you are the <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices</hi> or Judges of Gods <hi>Iſrael,</hi> a people precious unto him: who ſhould be afraid to be the keeper of Gods ſheep: <hi>Ioab</hi> bid be of good courage, and behave themſelves valiantly for their people, and the Cities of their God, 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 19.13. He that keeps the Church of Chriſt keeps that which will keep him: yea it is the Ark of the Lord which you are guarding, which guards them that carry it: as ſometimes when it was ſent homewards in a Cart by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> it was both <hi>auriga &amp; onus,</hi> as <hi>Theodoret</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves: <hi>Eſther</hi> need not ſhrink to ſpeake for the ſaving of that people, whoſe ſafety without her, was ſurer, then her own without ſpeaking for them, as <hi>Mordecai</hi> told her. And though it's not the leaſt part of your temptation that the ſucceſſe depends much upon people, who are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally as unſtable as waters: who may doe much either way, but are doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full whether: yet both theſe are in the hands of the Lord, who if he touch their hearts, they ſhall as one man flow and ſtick cloſe unto you: and doubtleſſe the faithfull in the Land, who are not of a double heart cloſe with your godly aimes and endeavours, and one of them is better then a thouſand others, and the Saints ſhall prevaile though it be by their death
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155227:6"/>to bring forth the Cauſe of the Lord Jeſus in his own time. But oh that I might aſpire farther in hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that the Lord, in whoſe hands are the hearts of Kings, would give you the heart and hand of his Anointed, to joyne with his Nobles and people to bring back the Ark with <hi>David</hi> to its place: and that He would at length ſay, that which I am perſwaded he might ſay in his very heart, The inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> are my ſtrength in the Lord their God: and alas! that in the mean time his ſoule dwells among thoſe, who are <hi>Apollyoniſts,</hi> children of the curſe, &amp; the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Gods wrath, of whom we might ſay, <hi>Depart from their Tents, leaſt, &amp;c.</hi> and with <hi>Iaacob, ô my ſoule come not into their ſecret:</hi> The Lord perſwade. As for your ſelves, whom the Lord hath hitherto maintained conſtant, and faithfull to his Cauſe, though with the extreame hazzard of your perſons, families, eſtates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the midſt of ſuch multitudes of your ranke that follow the wind, yea a body of people, which through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and prophaneneſſe, are enemies to the pure and exact ways of our Lord Jeſus, the Lord remember you, and wipe not out any of your kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to the houſe of your God; yea the Lord is with you, and you are laying that ſtone, which hath ſeven eyes, which run through the whole earth, to watch for you, and moſt wiſely and proſperouſly to carry on your work about it to perfection in his ſeaſon: Feare not, but let your hands be ſtrong, you fight the battels of the Lord, and (I truſt) evill hath not been found in your (no not in your hearts towards his Anointed) He ſhall bind up your ſoules in the bundle of life, but the ſoules of the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieres ſhall be flung out as out of the midſt of a ſling. Only may I humbly ſuggeſt my ſuite, that no unbeleeving feares, nor enſnaring flatteries of men wiſe according to the fleſh, cauſe you to make haſte, or turne aſide ſhort, or into any crooked ways: but make through work, as tender hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> and liſten not to <hi>Samaritan</hi> worſhippers any more, as formerly others have: <hi>Placet mirum in modum noſtrae carni</hi> (ſaith <hi>P. Martyr</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.) <hi>in duas partes claudicar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: quod eſt Deo, quam odioſiſſimum. Civiles homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, quòd in Reformatione leniter agere volint, cauſam adducunt, quòd tumultus horrent, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſeditiones. Ideò ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuadent ad multa connivendum eſſe: Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum alia eſt ſeveritas verbi Dei. Moſes</hi> was ſo ſtrict, and yet it was but faithfulneſſe, as to ſtay 600000. men, then leave one hoofe behind him, for that it might be for ſacrifice in ſervice of the Lord. It's true, Prudence directs <hi>quibus medijs,</hi> to preſſe and put on the work of the Lord: but Piety admits not of any fitting of Religion or the Kingdome of Chriſt to times, places or perſons: His worſhip and Kingdome is not one framed for the plaine or perſecuting times of the Apoſtles: and another for the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155227:6"/>ſtately frames of Chriſtian polities be they never ſo great: All States muſt conforme to the Church, all Kingdomes unto Chriſts: <hi>Eccleſiam ad mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di normam Regnorum &amp; Statuum componere, eſt merè Domum tapetibus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodare.</hi> I know, the contrary hath been the profeſſed judgement of many, and I feare the practiſe and way of more inclines thereunto: But once I hope Chriſt ſhall in <hi>England</hi> be acknowledged All, and only in his Church, and it ſhall be the greateſt honour unto him to accept him in every of his laws and priviledges: And give me leave to uſe the like ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentation that <hi>Bucer</hi> (whoſe piety in his works <hi>de Regno Christi,</hi> is worth the reading and obſerving at this time) to King <hi>Edward,</hi> you will not ſuffer any Parliament priviledges, or rights and liberties of ſubjects to be taken away, but will rather hazzard the loſſe of all: ſhall not zeale and punctualneſſe here be much more ſeaſonable and warrantable. I doe not think all will be ſeen at once, yet this ſhall be acceptable ſervice and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Lord Jeſus our King, if you aime at that one way, wherein he will be ſerved, and weigh all in the ballances of the ſanctuary, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the wiſedome and authority of his word therein above civill po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, humane reaſon, yea univerſality or antiquity of any practiſe ſince the firſt &amp; normall patterne preſcribed in the doctrine, &amp; recorded in the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the ſacred Scriptures. And I am perſwaded thus much being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, for truth, and ſincerely profeſſed as your ſcope, and aimed at in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, it ſhall be acceptable unto the Lord, and a bleſſing to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Pardon my boldneſſe good Sir, if I preſent to your wiſeſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the unhallowed paſſages that come forth in <hi>Mercurius Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus,</hi> of ſcornefull diſhonour put upon the Name and Perſon of Him, who is by you acknowledged the Lords Annointed: It's very aimeable to reade tearmes of honour put upon his Majeſty, though ſo farre ſtirred up againſt you: It's that which I meddle not with, what is caſt upon thoſe that are about the King: I deeme juſt to make Remonſtrances, as things ſtand, wherein even the actions of his Majeſty may be complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of for your juſtification: but to put bitter and moſt contemptuous ſcoffes upon His royall Perſon, is that which <hi>Davids</hi> heart could not beare: nor will your ſelves if you take notice of it, I am aſſured, and know the offender. It's againſt not only the courſe of Scripture, but one Article of the late Covenant. Though I am thus bold to mention what flies about; yet I am not ſo bold as to accuſe any of that Honourable Houſe herein, who may be farre from the knowledge hereof. Since my ſetting pen to paper; we heard ſo ſad newes as made me lay aſide my
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155227:7"/>pen, fearing no paſſage would be to you: but ſince againe, much better, bleſſed be the God of our mercy, that would not let us ſinke in ſorrow: and the comfort of our comfort is in the religious and bleſſed Covenant made by you and the <hi>Scottiſh:</hi> which He who hath wrought it graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accept it, and ſcale it in all hearts, and give us all with you not to make the emphaſis of our Joy, that it is made with the <hi>Scottiſh,</hi> but that its made by them and you with the great God of Heaven: that ſinne is ſo humbly acknowledged, ſo holily diſavowed and divorced, and Gods truth and ſervice ſo zealouſly avowed and profeſſed. It's the way whereby Kings have ſought and found the Lord: and whereby <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi> ſetled the peace of a troubled State. You have to all the world avouched the Lord for your God, now we looke for Him to avouch you for His people in the ſight of the world: And now our hearts have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſome good hold to wreſtle with the Lord, which we poore worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe wormes deſire to doe, ſo, as your expectations may not be failed of us: nor our duties towards you, on whom the eyes of the world are ſet: and in whoſe hands is the Cauſe of God, and the great action of this age for his Church: and in this purpoſe and poſture I ſhall humbly take leave, and with all due ſervice and honour to your ſelfe, and worthy Mr <hi>M.C.</hi> the only one, that I have had acquaintance with, in that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe, which hath now ſome yeares been more your houſe, then your own home where that worthy and vertuous conſort, and ſweet hopefull children were wont to accompany you, to whom with moſt affectionate reſpect I deſire to be remembred, I commit you to the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh, who hath honoured you with his higheſt work, and will crowne you with an immortall reward through Chriſt Jeſus, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ipſw.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 17, 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips obliged, but eſpecially in the Cauſe of our Lord Jeſus, NATH. ROGERS.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
